Finding Aid for Health System (University of Michigan) publications, 1892-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Health System (University of Michigan) publications 1892-2006
University of Michigan. Health System.
0236 Bimu C500 2
The Health System publications contain materials from University Hospital, University Hospitals, University of Michigan Medical Center (UMMC), University of Michigan Health System (UMHS), C. S. Mott Children's Hospital, and the Women's Hospital. The publications include annual reports, bylaws, brochures, manuals, directories, reports, and newsletters dealing with different aspects of the health system including administration, development, facilities, marketing and outreach, nursing, and services.
10 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
First accessioned in 1947 from Donor no. 2289.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The publications are open without restriction.
The three University of Michigan Hospitals--University Hospital, C.S. Mott Children's Hospital, and Women's Hospital comprise the core teaching facility for the Medical School. The Health System also includes a network of 30 health centers and 120 outpatient clinics located throughout the region and handles more than one million outpatient visits and 35,000 inpatients annually. The University Hospitals are a training resource for approximately 4,000 students a year.
The Health System is affiliated with the University of Michigan Medical School and the Schools of Dentistry, Nursing, Public Health, Social Work, and the College of Pharmacy.
Facilities
When the Department of Medicine and Surgery at the University of Michigan first held classes in the fall of 1850, the medical course consisted exclusively of lectures over a six-month term. Six months of training under a qualified physician were required following the school term. The first university hospital was not opened until 1869, in order to provide clinical instruction concurrent with classroom lectures. Located on North University Avenue, it was the first university-owned hospital in the United States and consisted of the former residence of a professor converted into a twenty-bed ward.
The Campus Pavilion Hospital, providing sixty beds, was built in 1875 to replace the original hospital. It consisted of two frame pavilions 114 feet long and 30 feet wide, and had few of the amenities (such as good ventilation and an operating room) viewed as essential soon after the hospital was erected--members of the faculty were lobbying for a replacement almost from the first. Starting in 1897, the Hospital remained open throughout the summer, as a condition for continued state support, initially granted in 1877.
In 1891, the pavilions were replaced by the Catherine Street Hospital, recognized in 1900 as the largest teaching hospital in the country. It was originally comprised of two main structures, one for the Department of Medicine and Surgery and one for the recently established Homeopathic Medical College The Homeopathic College moved to its own facility on North University in 1900, and its wing of the Catherine Street Hospital became the Surgical Ward, the other, the Medical Ward. When University Hospital eventually replaced it, the "old Hospital group" consisted of twenty buildings. An innovative and effective contagious disease ward was erected in 1897, the Palmer Ward for pediatrics in 1906, and the Psychopathic Hospital, with 40 beds, was completed in 1906 to be run by the state until 1937 when the legislature turned it over to the University.
University Hospital ("Old Main") replaced the group on Catherine Street in 1925, and provided 700 beds for the practice and teaching of medicine. It remained for almost sixty years. The world's first successful lung removal was performed by University of Michigan physicians in 1932, and the first heart transplant in Michigan was performed there in 1968. Additional facilities added included two additional floors devoted to tuberculosis in 1931, and the Neuropsychiatric Institute in 1937.
During the September 1958 meeting of the Board of Regents, the Bylaws were changed to reflect the naming of the medical campus (Medical School, University Hospital and School of Nursing) to the University of Michigan Medical Center. Research buildings and specialized hospitals and outpatient clinics were added over time to supplement the Medical Center's facilities. The Women's Hospital opened in 1950 and Adolescent Psychiatric Hospital in 1955. Pediatric wards in University Hospital were replaced in 1969 with the C.S. Mott Children's Hospital, and the James and Lynelle Holden Perinatal Hospital was built in 1972 to provide care for premature and critically ill infants. W.K. Kellogg Eye Center, a 32-bed facility providing patient care, education and research in eye diseases, was established in 1976. Kellogg Eye Center has since become an outpatient facility.
Despite the new construction, the Hospitals were still unable to support the growing training needs of the Medical School. Several affiliated--or "core"--hospitals were recruited to offer resources to University of Michigan medical students. The core hospitals included St. Joseph Mercy Hospital, Veterans Administration Hospital (Ann Arbor), Wayne County General Hospital, and Henry Ford Hospital (Detroit.)
The Replacement Hospital Project--in planning stages throughout the 1970's--began in 1978, culminating in 1986 with an 11-story, 550-bed adult general hospital. Attached to University Hospital is the A. Alfred Taubman Health Care Center, where patients are seen in 120 outpatient clinics.
Since then, the Medical Center has continued to expand. In 1990, services for women and children were integrated with new and renovated space amounting to 221,000 square feet. In the mid-1990's, Women's Hospital opened a 22-room Birth Center where women could keep a private room throughout labor, birth and recovery. The Cancer Center and the Geriatrics Center moved into a new building in 1997.
In 1996, the Medical Center was renamed the University of Michigan Health System.
Administration
In 1869, Dr. Abram Sager submitted a memorandum outlining the functions and principles of the University Hospital. He maintained that all patients applying to the hospital for care would submit to be utilized for clinical instruction, and that no patient be turned away because of an inability to pay. However, for many years the Regents controlled the financial operations of the hospital in order to ensure that patients were charged an amount sufficient to cover the cost of maintenance, because they insisted the hospital be self-supporting. For a period, between 1877 and 1918, income was supplemented by state support.
Day-to-day supervision of the hospital was carried out by the Hospital Superintendent. The position became a part of a more systematic administration in 1891, after the completion of the Catherine Street Hospital. Joseph Clark was appointed in 1888, his son, Harry W. Clark in 1897, E.S. Gilmore in 1900, and Jay B. Draper in 1908. Draper administrated a rigid payment policy that resulted in a surplus for the hospital which raised concern among the medical faculty. Though there had always been hospital committees of the medical faculty, their power had been limited. But partly in reaction to the surplus, and with the approval of the Regents, a new Hospital committee was created in 1912 to direct all medical affairs of the Hospital. Dr. Reuben Peterson, chairman of the committee, was made Medical Director.
In 1917, it became evident that a member of the medical faculty could not contribute enough time to the position of Medical Director, and a new Medical Superintendent and Director, Dr. Christopher G. Parnall, was appointed to give all of his time to the affairs of the Hospital. He was responsible for much of the plan and design for the new University Hospital. He resigned in 1924. Dr. Harley Haynes followed Dr. Parnall. Haynes--who was given the title, Director of University Hospital--put the new University Hospital into operation. He retired in 1945 and was succeeded by Albert Charles Kerlikowske. In 1969, Edward J. Connors assumed the position.
Also in 1969, President Fleming appointed the University Hospital Study and Advisory Committee, chaired by Fedele F. Fauri (sometimes referred to as the Fauri Committee), to study the administration of the medical campus. The committee recommended that the Medical School and the hospitals be administered together by a single person, the Director of the Medical Center. The Regents accepted the recommendation and appointed William N. Hubbard, Jr.--who was also Dean of the Medical School--to the position.
Hubbard served until 1970, when John A. Gronvall succeeded him in both positions. Gronvall, in 1974, dismantled the administrative changes initiated by the Fauri Committee, and the Director of the Medical Center position was abolished. In the same year, Connors resigned as Director of University Hospital after an audit of his travel expenses, and Jeptha Dalston stepped into his place.
When Gronvall resigned in 1982, having served his last eight years only as dean, President Shapiro took advantage of the change in leadership to reintegrate the administration of the Medical Center. He created the position of Vice Provost for Medical Affairs in 1984, and George D. Zuidema was appointed. The Dean of the Medical School and the Executive Director of the University Hospital reported to Zuidema, who in turn reported to the Vice President for Academic Affairs.
Dalston retired in 1985, and was replaced by John D. Forsyth, whose title was Executive Director of University of Michigan Hospitals. Zuidema retired in 1994, and Rhetaugh Dumas was appointed to his position, with the new title of Vice Provost for Health Affairs.
The mid-1990's saw the beginnings of drastic change in health provision. Managed health care and capitation--where the health provider, instead of the health insurer, takes on the financial risk--threatened upheaval, especially for an academic medical center. In order to remain competitive, management of the University Hospitals was reconfigured to imitate that of a corporation. In 1996, the University of Michigan Health System was created, and to John Forsyth's position was added the title, President and Chief Executive Officer of the Health System.
Later that year, Forsyth resigned, and Larry Warren was appointed, first on an interim basis, and later, permanently, as Executive Director of U of M Hospitals, and President and Chief Executive Officer of U.M.H.S. Douglas L. Strong replaced Warren as Chief Executive Officer in 2005.
Dumas resigned in 1997, and the position was once again renamed. Gilbert Omenn was appointed as Executive Vice President for Medical Affairs. One of three executive vice presidents at the university, Omenn reported directly to the President. President Mary Sue Coleman appointed Robert P. Kelch to the Executive Vice President for Medical Affairs position in 2003.
The Health System publications contain materials from University Hospital, University Hospitals, University of Michigan Medical Center (UMMC), and University of Michigan Health System (UMHS). Though "University Hospitals" is an entity which has existed in the past and does exist concurrently with UMMC and UMHS, it is not treated here as a sub-unit, because it is often used interchangeably with "Medical Center" or "Health System" on publications.
The publications of the Medical School (part of the Health System) and the academic and research departments of the Health System (such as the Department of Surgery and the Department of Pediatrics and Communicable Disease) are held in separate publications groups.
The publications collection consists of eight series. Six series deal with different aspects of the health system: Administration, Development, Facilities, Marketing/Outreach, Nursing Services, and other Services. Two series deal with additional hospitals within the University Health System: C. S. Mott Children's Hospital and Women's Health (Women's Hospital).
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Health System.; University of Michigan. Medical Center.; University of Michigan. Hospitals.; University of Michigan. Cancer Center.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Dietetics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Pharmacy Services.; University of Michigan. Replacement Hospital Project.; University of Michigan. Transplant and Health Policy Center.; University of Michigan. Turner Geriatric Center.; University of Michigan. Medical Center. Alumni Society.; Medical care--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Medical Center.; University of Michigan. Hospitals.; University of Michigan. Cancer Center.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Dietetics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Pharmacy Services.; University of Michigan. Replacement Hospital Project.; University of Michigan. Transplant and Health Policy Center.; University of Michigan. Turner Geriatric Center.; University of Michigan. Medical Center. Alumni Society.
Genre/Form:
Annual reports.; Pamphlets.; Directories.; Newsletters.; Proposals.; Reports.
- Administration 1892-2003, 4.25 linear feet
  The Administration series (4.25 linear feet, 1892-2003) includes publications relating to the staff and the policies and procedures of the hospital and health system.
  - Annual reports
    - Annual Report of the University Hospital, 1892-1945, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Report of the University Hospital, 1958/59, 1966/67 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report: The University Hospital, 1971-1977 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report, 1978-1984, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Biennial Report, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws
    - Bylaws, Rules and Regulations of the Medical/Dental Staff of the University of Michigan, 1974/75-1976 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws, Rules and Regulations of the Medical Staff of the University of Michigan, 1979-1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Directories
    - Referring Physicians Directory to the University of Michigan Hospitals, 1980-1983/1984 1997 (Box 1)
    - Telecare Health Information Directory, 1995-1998 (Box 1)
    - Telephone Directory: University of Michigan Medical Center, 1958, 1964 (Box 1)
    - The University of Michigan Hospitals Directory, 1990-1992/93 (Box 1)
    - The University of Michigan Hospitals Telephone Directory, 1982/1983-1989 (Box 1)
  - Employees
    - Affirmative action reports and guides 1979, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Brochures (Box 1)
    - Directory of Services, 1978, 1987 (Personnel Office/Human Resources Department) (Box 1)
    - Employee guides and manuals 1958, 1985, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
    - House Officers Association (Box 1)
    - Intern and Resident Handbook, 1963 (Box 1)
    - M-Fit, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Newsletters
      - Applause!, 2000-2003 (Box 1)
      - Clerical Update, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
      - Focus on Human Resources, 1983 (Box 1)
      - Hospital Star newsletters
        (known as: University Hospital Star, University of Michigan Hospital Star, Hospital Star, Star, University of Michigan Hospitals Star, University of Michigan Medical Center Sta r, University of Michigan Health System Sar)
        (consult MIRLYN for specific item holdings)
        - v.1 (1947/1953)-v.46 (1997/1998), 41 folders (Box 2)
        - v.47 (1998/1999)-2002/2003, 8 folders (Box 3)
      - Medical Center Clinicians' Group Newsletter, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
      - Medical Staff Briefings, 1988-1990 (Box 3)
      - Medical Staff News, 1984 (Box 3)
      - University Hospital Physicians' News, 1966-1974, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Office of Human Resources Development / Office of Training and Development / Office for Organizational Effectiveness
      - Programs and Services, 1985-1997 (Box 3)
    - Performance Planning and Evaluation: The University of Michigan Hospital's Approach, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Total Quality Diversity program
      - Four-year progress report (Box 3)
      - Report 1996 (Box 3)
      - Task force report 1991 (Box 3)
      - What Do I Do First? A Manager's Guide for Introducing Diversity Appreciation, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Histories (Box 3)
  - Management
    - Program for Excellence (previously the Quality Management (QA) Plan)
      - Advisors meeting agendas 1994 (Box 3)
      - Hospital Quality Assurance Program Governance Report, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Hospitals' Quality Assurance Program 1990-1991 (Box 3)
      - Hospitals' Quality Management Report / Hospitals' Program for Excellence Report, 1994-1997, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Program for Excellence, draft and plan, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Supervisor's guides (employee discipline, reduction-in-force) 1993-1996 (Box 3)
    - Total Quality Process
      - Telesis Journal, 1989-1991 (Box 4)
      - Total Quality Process Plan, 1990 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan Hospital Management Report, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Policies and Procedures
    - Administrative Orientation Manual, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Admission Guidelines 1989-1991 (Box 4)
    - Briefing Manual
      - 1990, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1993 (Box 4)
    - Diagnostic Procedures Manual, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Disaster Outline, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Guide to Security & Safety Services at UMHHC undated (Box 4)
    - Guiding Principles, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Isolation/Precautions Guidelines for University of Michigan Hospitals, 1987 (third edition) (Box 4)
    - Main Hospital and Kellogg Eye Center Non-clinical Policies and Standards, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Medical Record Documentation Guidelines 1996 (Box 4)
    - Mission and Role Working Statement, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Policy and procedure manuals
      - Volume I: Administrative 1983-1991 (Box 4)
      - Volume VI: Clinical Diagnostic 1974-1983, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Volume VII: Clinical Patient Management 1983-1989, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Volume VIII: Clinical Nursing Practice 1979-1986, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Religious Care for Hospital Patients: a Manual for Nurses and Doctors, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Short stay program, policies and procedures 1994 (Box 5)
    - Therapeutics Manual, 1976 (Box 5)
    - UH/Kellogg Operating room and Post Anesthesia Care Unit Manual, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Reports
    - The Economic Impact of the University of Michigan Medical Center 1986 (Box 5)
    - Position Paper in Support of University Hospital Cost Increase Ceiling Appeal to Blue Cross-Blue Shield of Michigan, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Three-year Statistics 1991/1994-1992/1995, 2 folders (Box 5)
- C. S. Mott Children's Hospital 1966-2006, 0.25 linear feet
  The pediatric wards of the University Hospital were replaced in 1969 with the C. S. Mott Children's Hospital. The publications found in C. S. Mott Children's Hospital series (0.25 linear feet, 1966-2006) consist of annual reports, directories, newsletters and brochures relating to the planning and operations of the Children's Hospital. Mott publications include Annual report, Brochures, Department of Neonatology handbooks and manuals, Directories, Newsletters (including The Exchange, the magazine of Mott Children's, Women's, Holden Perinatal, Psychiatric Hospitals).
  - Annual report 1998-1999 (Box 5)
  - Brochures
    - C. S. Mott Children's Hospital (Folder 1)
    - General (Box 5)
    - Opportunities for Children..., [1966] (Folder 1)
      (planning brochure for C. S. Mott)
  - Department of Neonatology
    - Holden House Staff Handbook: a Guide to Neonatal Intensive Care
      - 1st edition, [1979] (Box 5)
      - 2nd edition, [1980] (Box 5)
      - 3rd edition, [1981/1982] (Box 5)
    - Newborn Services Manual: a Guide to Neonatology and Well-Baby Care
      - 4th edition, [1982/1983] (Box 5)
      - 6th edition 1984 (Box 5)
  - Directories (also includes Women's Hospital and Holden Perinatal Hospital) 1983 (Box 5)
  - Newsletters
    - The Exchange (the magazine of Mott Children's, Women's, Holden Perinatal, Psychiatric Hospitals), 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Cares, 2001-2006 (Box 5)
    - Newsletter, 1996 (Box 5)
    - Update, 1998 (Box 5)
- Development 1982-2003
  The Development series (0.25 linear feet, 1982-2003) includes publications and brochures relating to fundraising and capital campaigns for the Hospital including brochures and printed materials from various development campaigns, including Michigan Difference campaign and MomentUM)
  - Brochures (includes Michigan Difference campaign) (Box 5)
  - Development reporter (newsletter), 1990-1997 (Box 5)
  - Gifts of art, brochures and flyers 1990-1992 (Box 5)
  - MomentUM
    - Brochures (Box 5)
    - Executive Committee proceedings 1992 (Box 5)
    - Solicitation guidelines 1991 (Box 5)
    - Vital Signs (newsletter), 1989-1997, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Facilities 1961-1986
  The Facilities series (2 linear feet, 1961-1986) consists of publications relating to the planning and construction of the various facilities of the Health System, including the Replacement Hospital Project Planning and construction reports; Replacement Hospital project development and planning materials; and reports relating to uses of Main Hospital, St. Joseph Mercy, and Wayne County General Hospital
  - Brochures and dedications (Box 6)
  - Floor plans 1985 (Box 6)
  - Maps (Box 6)
  - Planning and Construction
    - Medical Center Planning Report: a Guide to Future Physical Development 1961 (Box 6)
    - Outpatient Clinic Building 1950 (Box 6)
    - Planning Status Report: University Hospital, 1968 (Folder 1)
    - Program Statement, 1977 and appendices, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - A Strategy for Renewal: a Progress Report of Long Range Medical Center Planning with Special Emphasis on the Problems of Clinical Resources 1973 (Box 6)
    - University Hospital Planning Report 1967 (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan Medical Center Building Conditions Study Vol. 1-3, 1971, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Working Draft of Long Range Plan 1972 (Box 6)
  - Replacement Hospital Project
    - Brochures (Box 6)
    - Executive Report, May 1981-January 1986, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Development (Box 7)
      - Replacement Hospital Project development binder (with full-color drawings and descriptions) (Box 7)
    - Main Hospital (reuse)
      - Certificate of Need Application for Replacement and Renovation of Selected Components of the University of Michigan University Hospital, 1979 (Box 7)
      - A Study of the Reuse of the Old Main Hospital, 1985 (Box 7)
      - Summary of Analytical Study on Reuse of Present Main Hospital, 1975 (Box 7)
      - University Hospital Reuse Study 2, 1984 (Box 7)
    - Newsletters
      - Activation Management Newsletter 1985 (Box 7)
      - Hospital Update 1977-1978 (Box 7)
      - RHP Report,1979-1984 (Box 7)
    - Planning
      - Analysis of Forecast Demand, 1982 (Box 7)
      - Block Plans for the Replacement Hospital Project, 1980 (Box 7)
      - Corporate Office Study: Surgery Wing, 1986 (Box 7)
      - Executive Summary of the Functional and Space Program, 1978, 4 folders (Box 7)
      - Financial Planning Review, 1981 (Box 7)
      - Identification and Preliminary Planning of University Hospital Site Alternatives, 1974 (Box 7)
      - Telecommunications Planning Committee, informational mailing 1983 (Box 7)
    - St. Joseph Mercy
      - Certificate of Need Application for Renovation of Old St. Joseph Mercy Hospital Plant, 1979 (Box 7)
      - An Evaluation of the Feasibility of Acquiring the Use of the Present St. Joseph Mercy Hospital Site on a Short Term (3 to 5 years) Basis, 1977 (Box 7)
      - Summary of Analytical Study on Acquisition of St. Joseph Mercy Hospital Plant, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Wayne County General Hospital
      - [Contract Negotiations], [1974] (Box 7)
      - University of Michigan Hospitals Wayne County General Hospital Potential Acquisition Plan and Framework for Business Operating Plan: Internal Management Plan, 1983 (Box 7)
- Marketing/Outreach